Let's do it. Good morning Michael.
This is זבחים דף סב עמוד ב, Zevachim Daf Samech Bais Amud
Bais, 62.
We're going to start from
the eighth row. בשלמא. Bishlama. Let's do it. Good morning. All right,
so we're זבחים סב עמוד א, Zevachim Samech Bais Amud Aleph, eighth
line, בשלמא. Bishlama. So the גמרא Gemara asks: בשלמא בית מינכר צורתו
אלא מזבח מנא ידעי? Bishlama Bayis Minkar Tzurato, Ela Mizbei'ach Min Na
Yad'ei? The גמרא Gemara a few lines above was talking about how
אנשי כנסת הגדולה Anshei Knesses Hagedolah knew all kinds of things about
how to build בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, where to construct it, how
to change the מזבח Mizbei'ach a little bit from the מזבח Mizbei'ach
that משה Moshe built. And so the גמרא Gemara now asks, well
it's one thing, I can understand how the אנשי כנסת הגדולה Anshei
Knesses Hagedolah knew where to locate the מקדש Mikdash itself because מינכר
צורתו Minkar Tzurato you could see where the old foundations of the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash were. However, אלא מזבח מנא ידעי Ela Mizbei'ach
Min Na Yad'ei how did they know where to place the מזבח?
Mizbei'ach? I mean, it wasn't there anymore. אמר רבי אלעזר ראו מזבח
בנוי ומיכאל השר הגדול עומד ומקריב עליו. Amar Rabi Elazar: Ra'u Mizbei'ach
Banuy, U-Michael HaSar HaGadol Omeid U-Makriv Alav. So רבי אלעזר Rabi Elazar
said they had some sort of vision, they were able to see
the מזבח Mizbei'ach built in kind of some sort of נבואה, Nevuah,
and they saw מיכאל, Michael, the שר, Sar, or you know, as
the מלאך Malach giving a sacrifice on the מזבח. Mizbei'ach. Another opinion:
רבי יצחק נפחא אמר זה אומר דרשני. Rabi Yitzchak Nafcha Amar: Zeh
omer darshani.
Yeah, you know... Oh,
what's the... what does that mean? You know what I mean?
It reminds me of, you know, there with משה, Moshe, right? It
says: מזבח הזהב מקשה תעשה אותה Mizbei'ach Hazahav Mikshah Te'aseh Otah about
the מזבח Mizbei'ach or about the מנורה Menorah and משה Moshe didn't
know exactly how it was built, right? And then השם Hashem showed
him the צורה tzurah of the מזבח Mizbei'ach on... of the מנורה
Menorah and He said: כזה, Kazeh, right? So it kind of reminds
me of that a little bit, that רוח הקודש Ruach Hakodesh kind
of joins to help when it comes to building בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. Yeah, but there's you know מיכאל Michael who is probably שר
מליץ, Sar Melitz, you know, which shows that the קרבנות korbonot are
not meant to be, I imagine, like maybe, you know, I'm thinking
more like עולות Olot which aren't, you know, done for sin because
מיכאל Michael is מליץ יושר, Melitz Yosher, right? So, you know, and
I would say like, you know, what is he מקריב, makriv, you
know, what need do angels have for this? Like, you know, like
what was it? Like he was somehow on earth doing it? Like,
you know, what is that trying to say? Yeah, you're taking me
somewhere else actually. When בית המקדש של מטה Beis Hamikdash Shel Mata
doesn't exist, maybe it's what they're saying בית המקדש של מעלה... Beis
Hamikdash Shel Ma'ala... it elevates itself or it exists on an elevated
level of the מלאכים. Malachim. They take over, there's like a spiritual
version of בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash that happens. And then when ישראל
Yisrael come back to Israel and reconstruct the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
they kind of fill in the gap and rebuild בית המקדש של
מטה. Beis Hamikdash Shel Mata. And then you can talk about the
advantages and disadvantages. בית המקדש של מעלה Beis Hamikdash Shel Ma'ala can't
be destroyed, בית המקדש של
מטה, Beis Hamikdash Shel Mata, you know, the action of human beings.
Interesting. So okay, you have the מהרש״א Maharsha there. What does he
say? Just this is ירושלים Yerushalayim in heaven which corresponds to ירושלים
Yerushalayim on earth. תענית. Taanit. Each aspect of the heavenly ירושלים Yerushalayim
is erected above its... is directly above its earthly counterpart. God showed
them the heavenly altar so that they would know the position of
the earthly altar. It's kind of like VR, right? Virtual reality בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. But
so I'm trying to understand something. So are we still saying that
שלמה Shlomo couldn't figure out where it was? So I think this
is more like geography. I mean, the image I had in mind
is of 9/11. Right? So if you... it would be after 9/11,
it was easy and we can still see it today, there's two
holes in the ground more or less where the buildings were. But
it would be easy to imagine if you came there where the
buildings stood. But if you wanted to figure out where the halcar
that all the office workers used on a daily basis, that would
be really hard to establish. And then the question would be, how
do I know... and if you want to like bring the life
back, not only the building, you'd have to kind of ask: how
do I know where people used to hang out before the catastrophe
happened? Or להבדיל, lehavdil, how do I know where the, you know,
the מנחה מנין Mincha minyan was? So for that you need, you
know, רוח הקודש Ruach Hakodesh or... I mean, the next two examples
are kind of like that also. Let's just read them. But wait,
no, but I mean weren't we trying to answer... This is... I
think this is connected in the sense of how did אנשי כנסת
הגדולה Anshei Knesses Hagedolah know what they knew? Right. And before we
said: ויכינו המזבח על מכוניו Vayachinu Hamizbei'ach Al Mechonav that הגיעו לסוף
מדותיו. Hagiyu Le-Sof Midotav.
They had a deeper insight through their analysis of the כתובים Kesuvim
or through רוח הקודש Ruach Hakodesh than even שלמה Shlomo himself. Right,
but how? But שלמה, Shlomo, I thought שלמה Shlomo was the smartest
one. So how could he not have known?
That's my question. How... like, you know,
and רבי לונשיץ Rabbi Luntschitz had a דרש drash that
שלמה Shlomo represented תורה שבכתב Torah She-Bichtav and אנשי כנסת הגדולה Anshei
Knesses Hagedolah is the transition to תורה שבעל פה. Torah She-Be'al Peh.
And the idea is that even though תורה שבכתב Torah She-Bichtav is
sufficient and תורה שבכתב Torah She-Bichtav also gives you
exact idea of how it should be built, exact measurements, then comes
תורה שבעל פה Torah She-Be'al Peh and אנשי כנסת הגדולה Anshei Knesses
Hagedolah and they said oh, it could be built up to ששים
אמה. Shishim Amah. So תורה שבעל פה Torah She-Be'al Peh on the
other hand doesn't give you as clear-cut of an idea of what
it
should be. It is weird.
It is basically saying שלמה Shlomo *Shlomo* did it one way and
later, at the end of דף daf ס״ו עמוד ב׳ *Daf Samech-Vav
Amud Bet*, says שלמה *Shlomo* did it one way and in the
end לבסוף סבור ששתיה כאכילה *levasof savur she-shtiyah ke-achilah*. At first they
thought that the אכילה *achilah*, the blood goes directly into the מזבח
mizbe'ach *mizbe'ach* and the שתיה *shtiyah* of the sorry, the אכילה *achilah*'s
on the מזבח mizbe'ach *mizbe'ach* and the שתיה *shtiyah* goes to the
floor. And later they decided, no, שתיה *shtiyah* should be like אכילה
*achilah* and it should go directly into this like hole in the
מזבח mizbe'ach *mizbe'ach*. So they kind of changed the הלכה halacha *halakha*
on us.
So that was Rabbi Linder's... that was nice.
Okay. רבי Rabbi יצחק נפחא אמר *Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha amar*, אפרו של
יצחק הוא שמונח באותו מקום *afro shel Yitzchak hu she-munach b'oto makom*.
So they saw the אפר *efer* of יצחק *Yitzchak* that was placed
on the מזבח mizbe'ach, *mizbe'ach*, which goes into the, you know, the
עקידה *Akeida* imagery and I mean, the אפר *efer* isn't from the
עקידה *Akeida* but definitely it goes again קרבנות korbanot. *korbanot*, מכפרים *mechapprim*,
עולה *olah*, right? רבי Rabbi שמואל בר נחמני אמר *Rabbi Shmuel bar
Nachmani amar*, does he mean the ashes were scattered over like now
a שתי אמות Amot *shetei amot* by שתי אמות amot *shetei amot*
wider range? I think right. I don't know, you know, like in
like breadcrumbs? Yeah, I don't know, I don't know if that was...
it was that specific, but maybe it was smack in the middle
and then what the measurements were, right? When how do you know
how did they know it is שתי אמות amot *shetei amot* what?
If I were an architect, if I were... I mean, I think
they knew that the... this is not about the measurements, this is
about where to locate it. It is a little bit of a
different question. Still, if I were an architect, I'd give you the
parameters of the property. I wouldn't just tell you smack in the
middle. The מזבח mizbe'ach *mizbe'ach* is ריבוע ribu'a, *ribu'a*, so I think
it is a little more flexible and you can kind of build
around it. But that's a good question.
Okay, third opinion, and this is where I got the הלכה *halakha*
card imagery from. רבי Rabbi שמואל בר נחמני אמר *Rabbi Shmuel bar
Nachmani amar*: מכל הבית כולו הריחו ריח קטורת, ketoret. משם הריחו ריח
איברים *mi-kol ha-bayit kulo herichu rei'ach ketoret, mi-sham herichu rei'ach evarim*.
So the entire חצר *chatzer*, the entire area of the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash *Beit Hamikdash* which they knew where it was because of
the יסודות *yesodot* of the foundations smelled like קטורת ketoret, *ketoret* and
the only place that smelled differently was the מזבח mizbe'ach *mizbe'ach* where
it smelled like איברים *evarim* like the burnt like the burnt animal
parts. So to summarize this little piece, three opinions: one is that
they saw an heavenly image of מיכאל *Michael* giving a קרבן korban
*korban* right where it was, one was that they saw the אפר
*efer* of יצחק *Yitzchak* and one was that there was a different
smell: it wasn't קטורת *ketoret*, it was איברים *evarim* right in that
spot.
My mission for שבת *Shabbat* is to think about what each of
these opinions mean. So let's talk about it next week. The ashes
that they mentioned is probably the sacrifice of the ram rather than
יצחק *Yitzchak* himself. It is a little apologetic. It is interesting. Well,
you know, there was someone who's very fascinating between on ראש השנה
*Rosh Hashanah* actually, he gave, or yeah, he gave a שיעור *shiur*
about this that the מדרשים *Midrashim* that tend to develop that say
that you know actually it is not that the... no, it wasn't
but actually יצחק *Yitzchak* was sacrificed as well. Like yeah, that's what
the מדרשים *Midrashim* they actually say that. And he revived? Yeah. Interesting.
So you know and it could be some of these kind of
things that אפרו של יצחק *efro shel Yitzchak*, not אפר *efer*... you
know, that
some basically said that some מדרשים *Midrashim* like became more specific and
it is probably a function more of like you know Crusades and
a lot... right, as the martyrdom became... Yeah, I mean it is
weird. I was at a ברית *bris* right last Tuesday, we saw
each other, and we say להכניסו בבריתו של אברהם אבינו *le-hachniso bi-vrito
shel Avraham Avinu*. And we know that according to the story in
the תורה Torah. *Torah* the ברית *berit*, and we always use it
is clearly about... is about ברית מילה *brit milah*. Nonetheless, when you
have a baby on the בימה *bimah*, on the מזבח mizbe'ach, *mizbe'ach*,
a young child, the father comes, the מוהל *mohel* lifts a knife,
right, and he cuts something, it is hard not to think about
whether the subversive message of the ברית *berit* is also the ברית
*berit* of the עקידה *Akeida*. That is not clearly not the direct
פשט pshat, *pshat* of what ברית *berit* means, but that's what I
was thinking.
So totally goes back to יצחק *Yitzchak* and was יצחק נעקד *Yitzchak
ne'ekad*.
Okay. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי Rabbi, יוחנן *Amar Rabba
bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan*. רבה בר בר חנה *Rabba bar
bar Chana* said in the name of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*: שלושה
נביאים עלו עמהם מן הגולה *sheloshah nevi'im alu imahem min ha-golah*. Three
נביאים *nevi'im* came from the גולה *golah* with the people rebuilding בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash שני *Beit Hamikdash Sheni*. אחד שהעיד להם על המזבח
hamizbe'ach. *echad she-heid lahem al ha-mizbe'ach*. One who testified to them about
the מזבח mizbe'ach *mizbe'ach* this refers back to what we said before
that the size of the מזבח mizbe'ach *mizbe'ach* could be large up
to שישים אמה ama. *shishim amah*, up to sixty אמה ama *amah*,
larger than the מזבח mizbe'ach *mizbe'ach* that משה *Moshe* built and שלמה
*Shlomo* built. ואחד שהעיד להם על מקום המזבח hamizbe'ach *ve-echad she-heid lahem
al mekom ha-mizbe'ach*. One told them where the מזבח mizbe'ach. *mizbe'ach* should
be. So this is I guess a fourth answer to the question
of how did they know where it should go. ואחד שהעיד להם
שמקריבין אף על פי שאין בית bayit. *ve-echad she-heid lahem she-makrivin af
al pi she-ein bayit*. And one that told them the הלכה *halakha*
that you can start giving sacrifices even before בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
*Beit Hamikdash* is built. במתניתא תנא *be-matnita tana*, in a similar ברייתא
braita *Baraita* it is stated in the name of someone else, of
a תנא *Tanna* not of an אמורא *Amora*. רבי אלעזר בן יעקב
אומר *Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov omer*: שלושה נביאים עלו עמהם מן הגולה
*sheloshah nevi'im alu imahem min ha-golah*. Three נביאים *nevi'im* came up with
the בוני בית המקדש השני Beit HaMikdash haSheini. *bonei Beit Hamikdash Sheni*
from the גולה *golah*. אחד *echad*... them on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, one
testified about where the מזבח mizbe'ach. should be and ועל מקום המזבח,
ve-al mekom ha-mizbe'ach, one testified two things: one about where the מזבח
mizbe'ach should be and how and the size, the issue of how
big it can be. דחד שהעיד להם שמקריבין אף על פי שאין
בית, Dichad she-heid lahem she-makrivin af al pi she-ein bayit, one who
told them the הלכה that you're allowed to give a קרבן Korban
even though there is no בית. דחד שהעיד להם Dichad she-heid lahem
even though there is no בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, built yet. וחד
שהעיד להם על התורה שתכתב אשורית. Vechad she-heid lahem al ha-Torah she-tikatev
Ashurit. The third one told them something that isn't related to the
world of the מקדש, Mikdash, rather that the Torah, the fonts of
the Torah can be changed. So changed or revived.
One of the traditions in the תלמוד. Talmud. Not that it can
be changed, that it should be changed. Sorry, right. So one of
the, originally I
mean if you've seen old like writing from like the time of
יציאת מצרים, Yetziat Mitzrayim, the Hebrew lettering was different. That was the
כתב עברי. Ketav Ivri. And in the time of עזרא Ezra it
was either modernized or according to other traditions in the גמרא Gemara
it was revived to an alphabet that's kind of familiar to what
we use today. And that's called הכתב אשורי. haKetav Ashuri. But this
whole thing was a מחלוקת machloket about because if you say מקריבין
אף על פי שאין בית, makrivin af al pi she-ein bayit,
then that means as רש"י Rashi says, קדושת הבית קידשה לשעתה וקידשה
לעתיד לבוא, kedushat ha-bayit kidshe-ha l'shata v'kidshe-ha l'atid lavo, right, which is
a מחלוקת machloket though, we have that throughout ש"ס. Shas. Yeah, like,
and here we're saying oh yeah for sure.
So then it's what does any opinion do with that then? You
know, I guess they'll reject this מימרא. meimra. Yeah, but I don't
know, I think I don't know enough about what it means קדושת
הבית kedushat ha-bayit and the ability to give קרבנות. korbanot One is
the other, in other words because if you don't need, but
what they're basically saying is, right, since it's קדוש, kadosh, then pretty
much as good as there. Yeah, I agree. This is, yeah, I'm
not sure what the פשט, pshat, which is weird because then you
could say alright then why bother with the בית המקדש then if
you know we're מקריב makriv anyway.
But my more immediate question was this was like an ongoing מחלוקת
machloket in ש"ס Shas all the time.
And here they're just like, you know, here they're coming down on
one side of it so specifically you know
I would hope that we address this then. What does that... the
גמרא Gemara here at least doesn't go in-depth and nor do the
ראשונים Rishonim אליבא דאמת. aliba d'emet.
I don't see how they can but yeah, that's a great question.
And nor does ArtScroll I bet. Yeah.
At three, you know it's this Christian imagery, I don't know the
story, three wise men, beside these three prophets came up. Interesting. Yeah.
I don't know what that story, I don't know the details on
that but just the imagery is. Yeah.
And a Rabbi Owens or Popeye would have something to say about
the connection between the Torah, the changing of the fonts of the
Torah and as אנשי כנסת הגדולה Anshei Knesset HaGedolah reviving the old
world of בית המקדש and building בית המקדש השני. We also see
a נבואה nevuah referring to how the Torah is to be approached,
learned, it's made accessible, which is the other revolution in the times
of עזרא Ezra that we feel more today. Right. And there's another
note here saying that actually there's a dispute about whether the Torah
was originally given in אשורית Ashurit and then it was lost and
then עזרא Ezra reinstated it. Where is it... does it say what
מסכת masechet that appears in? It says סנהדרין Sanhedrin
21b and רמב"ם Rambam and
רש"י Rashi also,
you're right. Okay. סנהדרין כ"א ע"ב, Sanhedrin kaf aleph amud bet, great.
Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan.
Now we go back to מזבח mizbe'ach size. תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan:
קרן וכבש ויסוד וריבוע מעכבין, מדתו ארכו מדתו רחבו מדתו קומתו אין
מעכבין. keren v'keves v'yesod v'ribu'a me'akvin, midato orko midato rochvo midato komato
ein me'akvin. So
the top four corners of the מזבח, mizbe'ach their existence, and the
כבש, keves, the ramp, כבש, keves, the ramp, and the יסוד, yesod,
the bottom foundation, and the ריבוע, ribu'a meaning that the מזבח mizbe'ach
should be a perfect square, מעכבין. me'akvin. They if you don't have
that, the מזבח mizbe'ach is פסול. pasul. מדתו ארכו מדתו רחבו מדתו
קומתו, midato orko midato rochvo midato komato, the height, width, and length,
אין מעכבין, ein me'akvin, don't hold you back. מנא הני מילי? Mena
hanei milei? How do we know this? Because you know there's a
מחלוקת machloket as to what it was like anyway. Right. So there's
general criteria. מנא הני מילי? Mena hanei milei? How do we know
this? אמר רב הונא אמר קרא. Amar Rav Huna amar kra. Rav
Huna points to a פסוק, pasuk, it says המזבח. hamizbe'ach A few
פסוקים pesukim in the beginning in ויקרא ד' Vayikra dalet and ויקרא
ו' Vayikra vav use the phrase המזבח hamizbe'ach and he with an
extra ה' hei and he interprets that to say כל מקום שנאמר
המזבח לעכב. kol makom she-ne'emar hamizbe'ach le-akev. Wherever the phrase המזבח hamizbe'ach
appears is מעכב. me'akev. And רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi refers to the
three פסוקים, pesukim, says קרן המזבח, keren hamizbe'ach, so the קרן keren
is מעכב. me'akev. It says אל יסוד המזבח el yesod hamizbe'ach also
in ויקרא ד', Vayikra dalet, so the יסוד yesod is מעכב. me'akev.
And it says, it doesn't say המזבח ha-mizbe'ach. regarding the כבש, keves,
regarding the ramp, but it says אל פני המזבח el pnei hamizbe'ach
and רש"י Rashi explains that פני, pnei, the פנים, panim, the face
of the מזבח, mizbe'ach is the way you'd approach it, meaning the
ramp. Yeah. Okay. אלא מעתה כיור לרבי וסובב לרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
הכי נמי דמעכב דכתיב ביה. Ella me'atah kiyor l'Rabbi v'sovev l'Rabbi Yossi
b'Rabbi Yehuda hachi nami d'me'akev d'chtiv beih. So if you say that
every place where it says המזבח ha-mizbe'ach in the פסוקים. pesukim. אלא
מעתה ela me'ata כיור kiyor לרבי le-Rabbi וסובב ve-sovev לרבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה le-Rabbi Yose be-Rabbi Yehuda הכי נמי דמעכב hachi nami de-me'akev דכתיב
de-chtiv המזבח. ha-mizbe'ach So
if you say that every place where it says המזבח ha-mizbe'ach, in
the פסוקים, pesukim, that means that the item of the factor about
the מזבח mizbe'ach. that appears next to the word המזבח is מעכב,
me'akev, and this פסוק pasuk המזבח, does this mean that רבי and
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose be-Rabbi Yehuda would say that the
כיור kiyor and סובב, sovev, these two items regarding the מזבח mizbe'ach
are also מעכב, me'akev, also hold back from using the מזבח mizbe'ach
if they don't exist? Why would we think that? דכתיב de-chtiv because
it says in the פסוק pasuk ונתתה אתו תחת כרכב המזבח מלמטה.
ve-natata oto tachat karchov ha-mizbe'ach mi-lemata. There's a פסוק pasuk that says
and
you shall
give the decoration that net of decoration goes under an item called
כרכב. karchov. So the כרכב karchov is referred to כרכב karchov as
כרכב המזבח. karchov ha-mizbe'ach. So even if we don't even before we
even know what כרכב karchov is, we can assume that since it's
כרכב המזבח, karchov ha-mizbe'ach, whatever this כרכב karchov is, if it doesn't
exist, it's מעכב me'akev and you need to have the כרכב. karchov.
And now there's a מחלוקת machloket between the two תנאים tannaim about
what the כרכב karchov is. דתניא de-tanya איזהו כרכב? eizehu karchov? רבי
אומר זה כיור. Rabbi omer ze kiyor. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר
זה הסובב. Rabbi Yose be-Rabbi Yehuda omer ze ha-sovev. So רבי says
it's the כיור, kiyor, not to be mistaken with the כיור kiyor
the sink. כיור kiyor means a certain
decoration, a small decoration that was put on the top of the
מזבח. mizbe'ach. So if this is the top of the
מזבח, mizbe'ach we have that, so this is where the כרכב karchov
would be. It's some sort of decoration right over here and under
this is the מכבר michbar that net.
And רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says זה הסובב. ze ha-sovev. There was
some sort of סובב sovev up here, some sort of surrounding surrounding
like strip of מזבח. mizbe'ach רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר זה הסובב.
Rabbi Yose be-Rabbi Yehuda omer ze ha-sovev.
So going back to the question, the question was according to you,
if it says כרכב המזבח, karchov ha-mizbe'ach, does this mean that the
כרכב karchov
is מעכב, me'akev, the כיור kiyor or the סובב? sovev? So the
גמרא Gemara says yes, indeed. If you don't have the כרכב, karchov,
it is מעכב. me'akev. The מזבח mizbeach, would be פסול pasul without
a
כרכב. karchov.
דתניא de-tanya אותו היום נפגמה קרן המזבח והביאו בול של מלח וסתמוהו
ולא מפני שכשר לעבודה אלא שלא יראה מזבח פגום שכל מזבח שאין
לו קרן וכבש ויסוד וריבוע פסול. oto ha-yom nifgema keren ha-mizbe'ach ve-hevi'u
bul shel melach u-stamuho ve-lo mipnei she-kasher la-avoda ela she-lo yeira'eh mizbe'ach
pagum she-kol mizbe'ach she-ein lo keren ve-kevesh ve-yesod ve-ribu'a pasul. רבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה אומר אף הסובב. Rabbi Yose be-Rabbi Yehuda omer af ha-sovev.
So the גמרא Gemara brings a ברייתא braita here that refers to
a pretty famous story about a day when the מזבח mizbeach, was
פסול. pasul. The story goes as follows as far down in סוכה.
Sukka. We know that on סוכות Sukkot there's a special מצוה mitzvah
of ניסוך המים. nisuch ha-mayim. Now ניסוך המים nisuch ha-mayim isn't stated
explicitly in the תורה. Torah Most
ניסוכים, nisuchim, most libations are wine libations.
So the חכמים chachamim were דורש doresh that on סוכות Sukkot you're
מנסך מים. menasech mayim. You do a water libation and not just
a wine libation. Now the צדוקים Tzadokim who were more literal about
the תורה did not agree and there were various cases where צדוקי
כהנים Tzadoki Kohanim would resist pouring the water or instead of pouring
it on the מזבח mizbeach, they'd pour it on their feet. So
one day a צדוקי כהן Tzadoki Kohen did that, so all famously
I think it happens in another story as well with one of
the Herodian kings but in this case all the people took, all
the people came, grabbed their אתרוגים, etrogim, came their פטמים pitamim and
ורגמו באתרוגיהם ve-regamu be-etrogieihem threw their etrogim. Like Monty Python. Exactly. Exactly
with their אתרוג. etrog. The only problem is the מזבח mizbeach? wasn't
concrete, we saw it was built out of like lime. Well the
other thing is they also used rocks too. Oh really?
It says אבנים avanim there?
Oh, in that case even better. אבנים, avanim, I see that. I
see the note says אבנים. avanim. ורגמו באתרוגיהם. ve-regamu be-etrogieihem. I know,
but I remember also. Okay, great. So the אתרוגים etrogim hit the
כהן, kohen, the rocks hit the מזבח mizbeach, and the corner of
the מזבח Mizbeach broke. And they threw rocks at the guy
too and it hit the מזבח. Mizbeach So the corner of the
מזבח mizbeiach נפסל, nifsal, the קרן המזבח keren mizbe'ach was פסול pasul
and that same day they did a, they made a temporary fix,
they brought a בול של מלח bul shel melach and they fixed
it. But not because that fix didn't make the מזבח mizbeiach? usable,
but it at least was more כבוד kavod to the מזבח. mizbeiach
And then the ברייתא braita. continues and says שכל מזבח, she-kol mizbe'ach,
every מזבח mizbeiach that doesn't have the קרן, keren, the כבש, kevesh,
the יסוד, yesod, the ריבוע is פסול. pasul. That we know already
and here's the relevant proof, רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר אף הסובב.
Rabbi Yose be-Rabbi Yehuda omer af ha-sovev. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi
Yose be-Rabbi Yehuda explicitly says that if the סובב sovev was broken
or didn't exist the מזבח mizbeiach, would be פסול pasul to be
used and the גמרא Gemara assumes whether the סובב sovev is the
decoration according to רבי or the extra like little strip according to
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose be-Rabbi Yehuda it wouldn't matter. Whatever
the כרכב karchov is, it needs to be there. Okay, continuing with
the כרכב. karchov. So what is this כרכב? karchov? תנו רבנן. tanu
rabanan. Says a ברייתא. braita איזהו כרכב? eizehu karchov? בין קרן לקרן.
bein keren le-keren. בין קרן לקרן bein keren lekeren מקום הילוך רגלי
הכהנים אמה. mekom hiluch raglei hakohanim ama. So literally the ברייתא braita
says the following: What is the כרכוב? karkov? Between the two, between
one corner and the other, the place where the כוהנים's kohanim feet
are, or the place where the כוהנים kohanim walk, which is an
אמה. ama So the גמרא Gemara just asks a clarifying question: אטו
כוהנים בין קרן לקרן הוו אזלי? Atu kohanim bein keren lekeren havu
azlei? Wait a second, you're saying the place between the corners where
the כוהנים kohanim would walk? They can't walk around there. Why? It's
impossible. That's a wrong description. Why is that a wrong description? Because
if you look here,
if this is like an aerial view of the מזבח, mizbeiach you
can't walk between the קרנות keranot like that because you'd keep hitting
the corner. So really, where the כוהנים kohanim walked was here in
the one אמה ama here. Right? This is one, this is two,
and this is the middle one by one square where the where
the where the actual מערכה ma'aracha was. So it can't be that
this is the that this place is where the כוהנים kohanim walk.
So you say just one אמה ama by one אמה ama, square?
It had to be more.
That's the way it goes, right? Five by five. This is one,
so that's a strip of one. Then the other strip of one
is where the כוהנים kohanim walked, and מקום מערכה mekom ma'aracha was
one by one. It seems way too little for all these כוהנים.
kohanim. It's weird. Yeah. I mean, but then we just we had
a whole calculation about that. It could be four quadrants that were
five by five. Didn't we... Yeah, that's another opinion. Yeah. But this
is the פשט, pshat and the גמרא Gemara is going with that
here. So again, so the גמרא Gemara clarifies that what the ברייתא
braita meant is something a little different. אלא אימא, Ela eima, let's
clarify.
ומקום הילוך רגלי הכהנים אמה. U-mekom hiluch raglei hakohanim ama. So the
ברייתא braita. reads as follows: What is the כרכוב? karkov? Let's change
colors. What is the כרכוב? karkov? בין קרן לקרן. bein keren lekeren.
This area is the
כרכוב. karkov.
ומקום הילוך רגלי הכהנים אמה. U-mekom hiluch raglei hakohanim ama. In addition,
there's a place of אמה amah. where the כוהנים kohanim would walk.
Okay, that's the פשט pshat of the
ברייתא. braita, והכתיב, Vehaktiv, the גמרא Gemara asks: Wait a second, the
פסוק pasuk says: תחת כרכובו מלמטה עד חציו. tachat karkuvo milamata ad
chetzyo. Wait a second, it can't be that the כרכוב... karkov... so
right now based on the פשט pshat. of the ברייתא, braita. we
understand that the כרכוב karkov is up here. Which it was, because
it was on the bottom. Right. I mean not the bottom, you
can see that the כרכוב karkov but right, but if if the
מכבר michbar is over here below, so a little wreath means that
the כרכוב karkov should be on the side, not on the top.
So now, so a few answers to that question. Where was the
כרכוב karkov in that case? אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav
Nachman Bar Yitzchak, תרי הוו. trei havu. חד לנוי וחד לכהנים דלא
נישתקדו. Chad lenoy vechad lekohanim dela nishtakedu. There were two כרכובים. karkovim.
The one כרכוב karkov which the מכבר michbar refers to is a
decoration over here. It was either, according to רבי, it was a
whole like art deco thing going on there. According to רבי יוסי
בר רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yosi Bar Rabbi Yehuda, it was like a
real like modernist Bauhaus strip of like a square, and whoever lives
in Israel knows what we're talking about, Tel Aviv style. There was
another כרכוב, karkov, which was more of a safeguard, and this was
a little kind of fence over here which made sure that the
כוהנים kohanim didn't slip and fall. Could be wider, shorter, but that's
the כרכוב. karkov. That's the other כרכוב. karkov. So it was a...
where where do you see that it was a fence? Where's it
say fence? רש"י. Rashi. So חד לנוי וחד לכהנים דלא נישתקדו. Chad
lenoy vechad lekohanim dela nishtakedu. I'm looking at רש"י. Rashi. סביב הקיר
שעליה השמות... Saviv hakir she-aleha hashemot... וחד לכהנים דלא נישתקדו, vechad lekohanim
dela nishtakedu, ולמעלה בראש המזבח העמיקו סובב כמין חריץ עמוק דבר מועט
להיות להם שפתו היקף מעקה קטן סביב שלא יחליקו. u-lemala berosh hamizbeach
he'emiku sovev kemin charitz amok davar mu'at lihyot lahem sfato hekef ma'akeh
katan saviv shelo yachliku.
So it could
be... it wasn't that it was a fence, it was more inside,
engraved inside. Right. More accurately, if this is the side and this
is like... so this is one and this is like the top
אמה, amah
so here if we're looking at it from the middle of the
מזבח, mizbeach so here there was a little like... it was a
little deeper. Yeah. Okay.
It wasn't that this went up, it was that the inside went
down. Right. Especially if you think that the כרכוב karkov was like
some sort of like lattice work engraving, then it's the same idea.
You have like a little bit of an engraving there so it
gives you a little bit of traction on your feet. It's inside
also. I see. That makes sense. Yeah, I don't know if the
interior... that's interesting. But I never I didn't think
that that you're saying that the מחלוקת machlokes about the meaning of
the כרכוב karkov can apply equally to that כרכוב karkov and to
that כרכוב. karkov. So you could do it by extending the side...
creating a little
a fence by deepening the inside, or you could do that by,
like, you know, making a surface like we use on our steps
fence. Cool. That's a beautiful פשט. Pshat Wow. Okay.
ומידתו וכו'. U-midato ve-chulei. Okay.
ומידתו בו ומידת קומתו אין מעכבין. U-midato bo u-midat komato ein me'akvin.
So that's referring back to the ברייתא. braita We said a number
of things are מעכב me'akev and פוסל posel the מזבח, mizbeach but
the height and the width... sorry, the width and the length aren't
מעכב. me'akev. אמר רבי מני. Amar Rabbi Mani. רבי מני's Rabbi Mani
going to add a note to that: ובלבד שלא יפחתנו ממזבח שעשה
משה. U-bilvad shelo yifchatenu mimizbeach she-asa Moshe. That's true up to 60
as long as it doesn't go smaller than the מזבח משה mizbeach
Moshe built. And כמה, ve'kamah, how big was that מזבח? mizbeach. What
is that? אמר רבי יוסף
אמה. amar Rabbi Yosef amah. So Rabbi Yosef says אמה. amah So
then the people laughed. מחו עליה. machu alei. People laughed at him.
חמש אמות אורך וחמש אמות רוחב רבוע יהיה המזבח. chamesh amot orech
ve'chamesh amot rochav ravu'a yihiyeh ha'mizbeach. The פסוק pasuk says five by
five. Rabbi Yosef, what's wrong with you? Rashi in the top of
the דף actually refers that Rabbi Yosef was slight- had memory issues
in his old age, so people thought he was- he was missing
things. Oh, so you said before, but. Right, exactly. אמר ליה אביי.
amar lei Abaye. So Abaye was his תלמיד talmid and he said
דלמא מקום המערכה קאמר מר? dilma mekom ha'ma'arachah ka'amar mar? Maybe you're
referring to this middle square.
אמר ליה מאו דגברא רבא הוי ידע מאי קאמינא. amar lei mau
de'gavra raba havi yada mai ka'amina. You who are Abaye, a great
man, you know what I meant to say. קרי עליהו kari aleihu
and then Rabbi Yosef continued and gave a nasty nickname to the
other people who laughed at him, בני קטורה. bnei Keturah. He called
them sons of Keturah, so you're almost the sons- almost Jews, you're
the sons of Avraham but you didn't come just quite as far.
Well, also וישלחם, va'yeshalechem, right? That they were sent away, exactly. Get
away from me. יפה. yafeh. That's what I think he's also. יפה.
yafeh. And now we're going to see another little story where the
phrase בני קטורה bnei Keturah is used as a- to mock תלמידים.
talmidim. בני אחיו של רבי טרפון, bnei achiv shel Rabbi Tarfon, Rabbi
Tarfon's nephews, הוו יתבי קמיה דרבי טרפון. havu yatvei kamey de'Rabbi Tarfon.
They were sitting in front of Rabbi Tarfon, presumably studying with him.
פתח ואמר. patach ve'amar. Well you know, I'm sorry, I'm just thinking
about this, Keturah and then we're going to talk about קטורת. I
don't know if there's any connection there, but
I mean, not just קטורת, but you know, I'm just thinking, I
don't know, maybe I'm stretching too far, but just throwing it out
there. That's a good one.
What do we do with it?
Maybe nothing, but I mean, it could be just an insight into-
of all of all like puns and and and teases, why did
he use בני קטורה? bnei Keturah? Well, but also like, you know,
you smell nice but you've no substance to you because smell has
no substance. I don't know, you know. Which as opposed to אתרוגים
etrogim which have smell and substance. It's all coming together. So פתח
ואמר, patach ve'amar, sorry,
פתח ואמר, patach ve'amar, Rabbi Tarfon opened his mouth and said, ויוסף
אברהם ויקח אשה ושמה יוחני. va'yosef Avraham va'yikach ishah u'shmah Yochani. So
he he misstated the פסוק. pasuk. Rashi says he did it on
purpose because they were being they were like sleeping. Yes, sleeping. It's
kind of like a back in my days in בני עקיבא Bnei
Akiva in Israel. So there was a trick, a silly trick, but
if you thought your like חניכים, chanichim, your students weren't listening, they
said, start start telling the-
start talking about הרב קוק HaRav Kook and then start telling Snow
White, you know, wait until someone realizes you're totally... Did they really
say that? Yeah, I've seen people do it. But it
works, just because they're
like... אמרו ליה קטורה כתיב. amru lei Keturah ketiv. Hey, hey, it
says they answered, wait, it says Keturah. קרי עליה בני קטורה. kari
alei bnei Keturah. He called them the sons of Keturah. I don't
know what that says about his sister, right?
Okay. אמר אביי בר הונא אמר רב חמא בר גוריא. amar Abaye
bar Huna amar Rav Chama bar Guria. So a quote in the
name of Rav Chama bar Guria, גזירין שעשה משה ארכן אמה ורחבן
אמה ועוביין כמחק גודש סאה. gezirin she'asah Moshe orchan amah ve'rochban amah
ve'ovyan ke'machak godesh se'ah. So if we look back at our מזבח,
mizbeach,
let's use this. So we're talking about this spot over here. For
the קרבנות התמיד, korbanot ha'tamid, there was a מצוה mitzvah to have
two גזירי עצים, gezirei etzim, two pieces of wood that would be
here and on them are the עצי המערכה atzei ha'ma'arachah and on
them the the fire would be burned and the קרבנות would be
brought. Now we're getting the measurements for those, naturally. ארכן אמה ורחבן
אמה ועוביין כמחק גודש סאה. orchan amah ve'rochban amah ve'ovyan ke'machak godesh
se'ah. So if we logic it out- wrong, really they are two
wooden squares, one and on top of another. Okay? So they were
exactly אמה amah, and אמה amah. and they were quite thin. They
were like, I don't know, I don't have any utensil like that
I use at home. Rashi describes it as the kind of thing
you'd use to like straighten a pile of wheat.
That's a certain measurement. You haven't been straightening enough wheat? Yeah. I
was trying to think if there's anything like that I used when
I baked to like straighten the power pile of flour, but I
don't have anything like that. אמר רבי
ירמיה באמה גדומה. amar Rabbi Yirmiyah be'amah gedumah. So Rabbi Yirmiyah emphasized
that we're talking about a small אמה, amah like a lesser אמה.
amah
And the the reasoning being because if the כהנים kohanim were walking
over here and they only have one אמה amah which isn't so
wide anyway, the אמה Ama in the middle should be minimal- slightly
smaller than your full אמה Ama, size. אמר רב יוסף. amar Rav
Yosef. Rabbi Yosef questioned, ולאו היינו דתניא, ve'lav haynu de'tanya, didn't we
learn in a ברייתא braita
as follows? The ברייתא Baraita quotes a פסוק. pasuk. על העצים אשר
על האש אשר על המזבח. al ha'etzim asher al ha'esh asher al
ha'mizbeach. Famous פסוק pasuk in ויקרא Vayikra about
קרבן התמיד. korban ha'tamid. שלא יהו עצים יוצאים מן המזבח כלום. she'lo
yehu etzim yotzim min ha'mizbeach klum. Why does it say על העצים
אשר על האש אשר על המזבח? al ha'etzim asher al ha'esh asher
al ha'mizbeach? Why is that double-layered description? To make it clear that
the עצים etzim cannot protrude. move out of the מזבח mizbeach. at
all. They should fit exactly. So it's not exactly clear to me.
When I read the גמרא, Gemara, I thought the פשט pshat? was
that רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya was kind of assuming something, he was
saying, he was using his logic to deduce that this אמה Ama
that we're talking about should be a smaller אמה, Ama. and רב
יוסף Rav Yosef was saying, why do you need to deduce this
using your logic or your architectural like insight? It's clear from the
פסוק, Pasuk, the פסוק Pasuk gives you a לימוד Limud that teaches
that explicitly. Looking at Rashi and Tosfot, sorry, not Tosfot, looking at
Rashi, it seems that
there's some sort of difference between the אמה קדומה Ama Kduma that
רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya was talking about and the אמה Ama that
רב יוסף Rav Yosef was referring to, Rashi calls it I think
אמה מטומטמת. Ama Metumtemet.
But I'm not sure what that is. This is five טפחים Tfachim
instead of six. Oh yeah, a קדומה Kduma is five and not
six and then, oh, that would be interesting. So it's kind of
like saying, they refer to it in מנחות. Menachos. This is referenced.
Yeah, I guess it's kind of like when you get like a
building kit, with Lego that wouldn't be the case, but if you
get like a plane kit to build, so they could give you
a piece, you could have a piece that, if that's the piece,
you could have a piece that sits inside of it perfectly and
that would be six and that would be five, or you could
have something that, you know sometimes with those sets, you think it's
not going to fit in, but if you just push it a
little bit, it's fine. So maybe that's the, maybe that's the difference.
All right.
תנן התם, Tnan Hatam, it says in a משנה Mishna in
מסכת מידות. Masechet Midot. כבש שהיה לדרומה של מזבח אורך שלושים ושתיים
על רוחב שש עשרה. Kevesh shehaya lidoroma shel mizbeach orech shloshim ushtayim
al rochav shesh esre. So let's just get that on the board,
just so that we have a point of
reference. Okay. So this will be the מזבח mizbeach. and this is
our כבש. Kevesh. So if you could imagine there's a little 3D
there. Okay. So this is the
כבש. Kevesh. And the length was sixteen and the height was nine.
Okay. So if we have a side view, we're talking about nine
in height and sixteen in
width.
מנא הני מילי? Minale Mili? So now the מנא הני מילי Minale
Mili is referring not to the sizes, but to the דרום. Darom.
How do we know, this is south, this is north, this is
east, and this is west. How do we know that the כבש
Kevesh was here? מנא הני מילי, Minale Mili, אמר רב הונא, Amar
Rav Huna, אמר קרא, Amar Kara, the פסוק Pasuk says, ושחט אותו
על ירך המזבח צפונה, Veshachat oto al yerech hamizbeach tzafona, ושחט אותו
על ירך המזבח צפונה, Veshachat oto al yerech hamizbeach tzafona, שיהא ירך
בצפון ופניו בדרום. Sheyehe yerech batzafon ufanav badarom. So the פסוק Pasuk
says that you have to be שוחט Shochet the קרבן on the
ירך המזבח צפונה. Yerech hamizbeach tzafona. Now ירך Yerech is this part
of the human body, like top part of the leg. What do
you call that in English? Thigh. Thigh, thank
you. And the way he understands the פסוק Pasuk is that the
ירך Yerech should be facing the north and the face to the
south. So if we were to imagine our person, he's kind of
saying, this is where the head, the face is to the south,
and the legs are to the north, if you look at the
picture, this is kind of the way he imagines it. Okay? So
this is south, this is north. I have a question about the
dimensions. Here it says
thirty-two אמות amot long. Oh right, yeah, sorry. Right? Okay. Sixteen wide.
I was getting that, go ahead,
sorry. So the sixteen, so... This is thirty-two, right, and then this
is sixteen. No. No, it's the sixteen is just where you put
your, whatever that is, the width of the bottom. Okay, and that's
nine, and that's the actual אמה. Ama Okay, got it. Perfect. But
on the other one, the side view put thirty-two instead of sixteen.
On that side. Thank you. So why was I saying sixteen? Oh,
because of this. Sixteen is the width. Sixteen is the width. Right.
I can't even draw. Thank you. So our thirty-two אמה ama long
person who's sixteen אמה ama wide is lying with his head to
the south, thereby his ירך Yerech is facing north, right, that way.
And that's learned from the פסוק, Pasuk, ושחט אותו על ירך המזבח
צפונה. Veshachat oto al yerech hamizbeach tzafona. Why is that פסוק Pasuk
referring, how do we understand that פסוק Pasuk refers to the כבש?
Kevesh? Right, it says ושחט אותו. Veshachat oto. I don't know. What's
the full פסוק? Pasuk? ושחט אותו על ירך המזבח צפונה לפני ה'
וזרקו בני אהרן הכהנים את דמו על המזבח סביב. Veshachat oto al
yerech hamizbeach tzafona lifnei Hashem vezarku benei Aharon hakohanim et damo al
hamizbeach saviv. Yeah, so we have to look at the full פסוק
Pasuk and understand, I guess what I would have, what I would
have thought they would have done with that is... Oto ירך המזבח
צפנה, yerech hamizbeiach tzafonah, there's nothing there on the צפון, tzafon, and
so you have to put it, you can't put it on the
west, cause then, you know, you'd be... Oh right, we're talking about
the שיטה, shittah, exactly. We're basically what we're confused by is the
same thing. How does this פסוק, pasuk, this פסוק pasuk might teach
you something about the שחיטה, shechitah, implying basically you could do it
there, which means there can't be something, you know, blocking you. Well
that's what I would have thought. Right? And you certainly can't be
in the west because that's you then you're getting into, you know,
yeah, there, into the אהל ohel over there. And okay, but so
but the imagery ירך המזבח צפנה. yerech hamizbeiach tzafonah. Okay. Yeah, let's
wait, think about 15 minutes. אימא, eima, so now the גמרא Gemara
questions that, at the end of the last wide line, אימא ירך
בצפון ופניו בצפון. eima yerech batzafon ufonav batzafon. The fact that ירך
yerech has to be בצפון batzafon don't teach you that the face
should be north. You could have imagined a situation where the כבש
kevesh was here, okay, and and imagine it as like a standing
person, right, or lying that way, where the feet are still heading
here and the face is north that way. So in other words,
both ירך yerech and the face are on the north. Yeah. אמר
רבא רמי גברא אפי. Amar Rava rama gavra appei. So רבא Rava
said no no, but basically, sorry this is the wrong description, basically
if you were doing it in the north, you'd have a כבש
kevesh like this, okay, that's that, and the way they understand it
would be that you'd have a person kind of sitting like that.
Okay. And then this is the ירך yerech and that's the head
and then the face is north, right, ירך המזבח צפנה, yerech hamizbeiach
tzafonah, both the ירך yerech is facing צפון tzafon and the face
is facing צפון. tzafon. So how do you know, just by the
fact that the feet, the legs
should
be facing
north,
how
do
you know that we're
talking about a person sleeping with his on the south side of
the מזבח mizbeach and not
a person sitting upright on the north side of the מזבח? mizbeach,
Either way the legs would be facing north, the ירך yerech would
be facing north. So אמר רבא רמי גברא אפי. Amar Rava rama
gavra appei. So רבא Rava doesn't really give us an answer, he
says imagine someone lying on their back. אמר אביי אדרבה, Amar Abaye
adarabba, reverse, תריץ ואותביה אפי. taritz v'otevvei appei. Make the guy sit
up and and have it all in the north. So רבא Rava
answered, אמר ליה רבוע כתיב. amar lei ravu'a ktiv. It says that
the מזבח mizbeach, should be רבוע, ravu'a, רבא Rava understands that to
mean something about lying down with the כבש. kevesh. And אביי Abaye
answers, והאי מיבעי ליה דמיהוי רבוע. v'hai minei leih d'me'uv ravu'ei. The
רבוע ravu'a is not used to teach us anything about where the
כבש kevesh should be located or how what imagery we should use
to imagine where the כבש kevesh is. רבוע ravu'a is used to
tell us that the מזבח mizbeach, has to be square. רבא Rava
answers, מכדי מרובע, michdiv meruba, it doesn't say מרובע meruba which would
only teach us about square, it says רבוע ravu'a which teaches us
both. ולטעמיך, v'letamecha, רבא Rava says, sorry אביי Abaye says, wait ולטעמיך
מכדי רבוץ, v'letamecha michdiv ravutz, well it doesn't say מרובע meruba only,
but it also doesn't say רבוץ, ravutz, it doesn't say lying down
either. So רבא Rava finalizes his answer like this, אמר ליה רבוע
כתיב דמשמע הכי ומשמע הכי. amar lei ravu'a ktiv d'mashma hach u'mashma
hach. רבא Rava says no, the phrase רבוע ravu'a though it doesn't
say רבוץ, ravutz, is the perfect phrase to teach us both about
the dimensions, that it has to be a square and about the
way the כבש kevesh should be located like someone lying down. ותנא
מאי טעמא הכי, v'tana mai ta'ama hach, a ברייתא Baraita teaches us
where the כבש... kevesh... again where should the כבש kevesh be? A
ברייתא teaches us that it should be on the south from a
different place. דתניא רבי יהודה אומר ומעלותיו פנות קדים כל פינות שאתה
פונה לא יהו אלא דרך ימין למזרח. Detanya Rabbi Yehuda omer u'maalotav
pnot kadim kol pinot she'ata poneh lo yehu ela derech yamin lamizrach.
So the פסוק pasuk says, the פסוק pasuk uses the phrase with
reference to the dimensions of בית המקדש, ומעלותיו u'maalotav and the corners
should be פנות קדים, pnot kadim, should be turning to the right.
So kind of if we imagine if you're coming from south and
you make a right turn, that'll take you to the מזרח. mizrach.
So the assumption is that when coming up the כבש, kevesh, you
have to be able to make right turns that would take you
to the מזרח. mizrach. If you were coming from the north, you'd
be making a left turn to go to the מזרח. mizrach. That's
the פסוק. pasuk. כל פינות שאתה פונה לא יהו אלא דרך ימין
למזרח. kol pinot she'ata poneh lo yehu ela derech yamin lamizrach. So
you have to make when you approach the מזבח, mizbeach you should
be able to make right turns that will take you to the
מזרח. mizrach. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואימא שמאלה למזרח, ve'eima smola
lamizrach, the פסוק ומעלותיו פנות קדים pasuk u'maalotav pnot kadim has the
word turn, פנות, pnot, and has the the term מזרח mizrach to
the east. It doesn't say ומעלותיו פנות ימינה קדים. u'maalotav pnot yamina
kadim. It could be ומעלותיו פנות שמאלה קדים, u'maalotav pnot smola kadim,
it could be you have to make turns to the east but
left turns to the east coming from the north. לא סלקא דעתך,
lo salka daitach, that that's impossible. It has to be making right
turns to the north meaning that you should be coming at the
מזבח mizbeach the כבש... kevesh... They hate lefties. Well yeah, we have
other places where ימין yamin is is given weight. So how do
we know that it has to be the right? דתני רמי בר
יחזקאל ים שעשה שלמה, Detani Rami bar Yechezkel yam she'asa Shlomo, the
big basin, the מקוה mikvah that שלמה built. The פסוק pasuk says
about it that
עומד על שנים עשר. omed al shneim asar.
statues of cattle. שלשה פונים צפונה, shlosha ponim tzafona, three facing north,
שלשה פונים ימה, shlosha ponim yama, three facing west. ימה yama being
west because of the Mediterranean in Israel, שלשה פונים נגבה, shlosha ponim
negba, three turning south to the נגב Negev where there's no water,
therefore it's called נגב, Negev, it's wiped of water, ושלשה פונים מזרחה
u-shlosha ponim mizracha and three facing to the east. Now, this teaches
us כל פינות שאתה פונה לא יהו אלא דרך ימין למזרח. kol
pinot she-atah poneh lo yehu ela derech yamin la-mizrach. Why?
Because if this is the ים yam and we have three here,
three here, three here, and three here, and they're described going north
to east, right? So it says פנות pnot like this, פנות pnot
like this, eventually we go to the east. The way it's described
goes from north all the way around to the east, that teaches
us that you should always be going, making right turns to the
east, right? Make a right from north to west, make a right
from west to south, and eventually to east.
The גמרא Gemara says, well, האי מיבעי ליה לגופיה, ha-i mibayei lei
le-gufeih, that פסוק pasuk can't teach you a general rule about how
you should approach the east, whether it should be from the right
or the left. We need it to learn about how the ים
של שלמה Yam shel Shlomo was built. The גמרא, Gemara, no, it
can teach us this. Why? אם כן פנים פנים למה לי? im
ken ponim ponim lama li? It says multiple times שלשה פונים צפונה,
shlosha ponim tzafona, שלשה פונים ימה. shlosha ponim yama. If it was
only to teach us how that ים של שלמה Yam shel Shlomo
was built, it would have been sufficient to just say שלשה פונים
צפונה ושלשה ימה. shlosha ponim tzafona u-shlosha yama. The reason they say
פנים ponim again and again to teach us that this is how
you should make your turns, this is how you should make your
turns regarding ים של שלמה Yam shel Shlomo and this is also
how the כהן Kohen should be able to turn when he approaches
the מזבח mizbeach on the כבש. kevesh. Okay. אם
כן פנים פנים למה לי. im ken ponim ponim lama li. New
issue. שאל רבי שמעון בן יוסי בן לקוניא את רבי יוסי. sha'al
Rabbi Shimon ben Yosi ben Lakunya et Rabbi Yosi. So question. אומר
היה רבי שמעון בר יוחאי: omer haya Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai: אויר
יש בין כבש למזבח. avir yesh bein kevesh la-mizbeach. רבי שמעון בר
יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai says there was a little air right
here between where the כבש kevesh ended and where the מזבח mizbeach
was. אמר לו ואתה היאותה אומר כן? amar lo ve-ata hi-ota omer
ken? So he says I heard in the name of רבי שמעון
בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai that there was air, a little
air space between the כבש kevesh and the מזבח. mizbeach So he
answered, he said then wait, you're quoting it as if you don't
agree. ואתה היאותה אומר כן? ve-ata hi-ota omer ken? You don't agree
with
that? והלא כבר נאמר בפסוק ועשית עולותיך הבשר והדם. ve-halo kevar ne-emar
ba-pasuk ve-asita olotecha ha-basar ve-ha-dam. The פסוק pasuk says that you should
bring your sacrifices, your עולות, olot, the דם dam and the בשר,
basar, making an analogy, a connection between the דם dam and the
meat. מה דם בזריקה אף בשר בזריקה. mah dam be-zrika af basar
be-zrika. That teaches us that just like the blood isn't put directly
onto the ground, rather the כהן Kohen throws it, so too the
בשר basar should be thrown on. So the image is kind of,
let's use this כבש, kevesh, is that the כהן Kohen will kind
of stand here and throw the בשר basar onto the fire over
here. And that's learned from the analogy. The analogy teaches us throwing,
and throwing assumes that there's air space that you have to throw
over.
אמר לו, amar lo, he said no. שאני אומר בצד מערכה עומד
בצד מערכה וזורק. she-ani omer be-tzad ma-aracha omed be-tzad ma-aracha ve-zorek. True,
the analogy teaches us that just like you have to throw the
blood, you have to throw the meat, but it doesn't teach us
that there's a difference. You can stand on the מזבח, mizbeach on
the top of the מערכה ma-aracha itself and throw the meat onto
the fire. אמר ליה כשזורק למערכה דלוקה הוא זורק או למערכה שאינה
דלוקה הוא זורק הוי אומר למערכה דלוקה הוא זורק התם את דורק
התם משום דלא אפשר. amar lei keshe-zorek la-ma-aracha deluka hu zorek o
la-ma-aracha she-eina deluka hu zorek hevei omer la-ma-aracha deluka hu zorek hatam
at dorek hatam mishum de-lo efshar. She says no, it's obvious
that the mere action of throwing has to happen because we know
that the fire was already burnt. So no one's going and actually
putting it onto the fire, placing it without any air space, because
you'd burn your hand. So clearly you throw it from the מערכה
ma-aracha onto the מזבח. mizbeach Why do we need the special analogy
between בשר basar and דם dam to teach us another extra layer
of throwing? To tell us that there was also air space between
the כבש kevesh and the actual מזבח. mizbeach Yeah, you can't have
much. I mean, it's like, you know, a hair's breath. Exactly. Because
otherwise, you know, you don't want one falling, right? Mind the gap,
right? And yeah, and I think soon we're going to see פסוקים
pesukim about something else that teaches that it's also just about keeping
the מזבח mizbeach an independent square entity. So that's that. I mean,
you can still, you know, it doesn't make a, you know, you
can still throw it even if it's like right up to it.
I mean. Yeah, I don't
know. It's not completely clear. And anyway, you're throwing it from the
top of the מערכה ma-aracha not from the כבש. kevesh. It's strange.
But it brings the top of the מזבח, mizbeach not top of
the מערכה. ma-aracha. Top of the מזבח, mizbeach right, onto the מערכה
ma-aracha from the top of the מזבח, mizbeach exactly. Okay. Let's finish
up.
רב פפא Rav Papa had a different way of learning this. רב
פפא אמר כי דם. Rav Papa amar ki dam. Instead of going
with the פסוק, pasuk, he just makes a logical analogy. כי דם
מה דם אויר קרקע מפסיקו אף בשר אויר קרקע מפסיקו. ki dam
mah dam avir karka mafsiko af basar avir karka mafsiko. Ah, so
this is something else. It says that it's not only that you
need to throw it, it has to be thrown just like the
דם. dam. When you throw the דם, dam, you're throwing it and
there's no, and you're throwing it, the כהן Kohen stands on the
ground or whatever and there's and there's ground and then the מזבח
and the דם dam sort of flies over ground. So too the
בשר basar has to fly over ground, not only over the metal
that the מזבח is made out of. Okay.
Okay, last topic for today. אמר רב יהודה Amar Rav Yehuda שני
כבשים קטנים יוצאים מן הכבש shnei kvashim ktanim yotzim min hakevesh שבהם
shebahem הקטן שבהן hakatan shebahen פונים ליסוד ולסובב ponim layesod velasovev ומובדלים
מן המזבח מלוא נימא umuvdalim min hamizbeach melo nima משום שנאמר סביב.
mishum shene'emar saviv.
So, in addition to this main כבש kevesh that we know, there
were two extra כבשים. kvashim. One going up like this on the
right side to the סובב sovev and one I think going kind
of down from over here to the יסוד. yesod. One on the
right, one on the left. You know what I was just thinking?
Let's just finish this up and then, okay. Going direct
so there were two extra little כבשים kvashim and he adds that
you should know that even these כבשים kvashim weren't directly connected to
the מזבח but they were separated just a tiny bit. And why
did they have to be separated a tiny bit? Not because of
throwing issues, rather because משום שנאמר סביב mishum shene'emar saviv because the
פסוק pasuk about the מזבח says that it has to be סביב.
saviv. And סביב saviv teaches us kind of that you have to
be able to circle it with something, even with air or thin
streams. ורבי אבהו אמר רבוע. Ve'Rabbi Abahu amar revua. Rabbi Abahu says
we know that there was a little separation between these extra כבשים
kvashim not because they were סביב saviv rather because of the word
רבוע. revua. וצריכי למכתב סביב וצריכי למכתב רבוע. Ve'tzrichi lemicatav saviv ve'tzrichi
lemicatav revua. Both לימודים limudim are necessary. דאי כתב רחמנא סביב, De'ei
katav rachmana saviv, if the Torah only said the word סביב, saviv,
הוה אמינא hava amina דעגיל מעגל. de'agil ma'agel. We'd think that yes,
there has to be a little separation between the כבשים kvashim and
the מזבח but the מזבח itself could be round. כתב רחמנא רבוע.
Katav rachmana revua. Now we know that not only does it have
to be separate, it also has to be square. And the reverse:
דאי כתב רחמנא רבוע, De'ei katav rachmana revua, הוה אמינא hava amina
דאריך וקטין. de'arich ve'katin. We would have thought that it doesn't have
to be a perfect square,
it could be rectangular. כתב רחמנא סביב. Katav rachmana saviv. The סביב
saviv teaches us another aspect, not that we wouldn't know just from
the word רבוע, revua, that it has to have some sort of
perfection. Let's do this final piece. תנן התם Tnan hatam הכבש והמזבח
ששים ושתיים. hakevesh vehamizbeach shishim ushtayim. So, one more last drawing.
The כבש kevesh and the מזבח were sixty-two. So this is the
מזבח and this is the כבש. kevesh. This together is sixty-two.
The גמרא Gemara asks: הני שיתין וארבע הוו. hani shitin ve'arba hava.
That's weird, right? We know that the מזבח is thirty-two and the
כבש kevesh in length of sixty-two, together that makes sixty-four.
How could that be? What's the פשט? נמצא פורח אמה יסוד ואמה
סובב. Nimtza pore'ach ama yesod ve'ama sovev. So I think we talked
about this previously, there was a little dent here for the יסוד
yesod an אמה ama wide and a little dent here for the
סובב sovev an אמה ama. wide. So really,
this was thirty because two אמות amot, were swallowed into the מזבח
itself. And finally, אמר רמי בר חמא. Amar Rami bar Chama. Rami
bar Chama says כל כבשי כבשים שלוש אמות לאמה. kol kivashei kvashim
shalosh amot le'ama.
Anytime you wanted to create a כבש, kevesh, a ramp, you'd have
the elevation work as follows: you'd go one אמה ama up and
have three אמות amot to go that distance. חוץ מכבשו של מזבח
שהיה שלוש אמות ומחצה ואצבע ושליש אצבע בזקופתא. chutz mikivsho shel mizbeach
shehaya shalosh amot vametza ve'etzba vishlish etzba bezigufeta. With the מזבח the
elevation worked differently. It wasn't one a ratio of one to three,
rather it was a ratio of one to three and a half
אמות and an אצבע etzba and a third of an אצבע, etzba,
right? How do we know that? So we said this is nine
אמות, right?
The height is nine אמות the entire מזבח except for the קרן
keren and the width is thirty-two. So I mean if you do
the math, twenty-seven that's you get three if you go up to
twenty-seven, right? Three times nine, okay, and then you get another, you
divide the five into half so you get another nine halves. Okay,
so you're left with one half an אמה. ama, Every half an
אמה ama is... then רש"י Rashi helps us out here... חצי
אמה. chatzi ama. Yeah, so רש"י Rashi says the half an אמה,
ama
sorry,
so רש"י Rashi says אמה ama equals... sorry, חצי אמה chatzi ama
equals twelve
אצבעות. etzbaot. That makes sense because I mean every אמה ama is
six טפחים, tfachim, every טפח tefach is
how many אצבעות? etzbaot? Five אצבעות? etzbaot? I'm not getting the math.
Anyway, the bottom line is that you'd have twelve to divide... אמה
ama is twenty-four אצבעות. etzbaot. Twenty-four אצבעות. etzbaot. So how many אצבעות
etzbaot to a טפח? tefach? I
mean if
a טפח tefach four is is your hand, so it has to
be four or five. I'm going to say four, right? Because right,
twenty-four אצבעות etzbaot and it's six טפחים, tfachim, yeah.
So every טפח tefach has four אצבעות etzbaot I think? Four. Yeah.
Perfect. So one אמה amah has...
maybe the reason why I said an
אמה amah is six or or you know four... So bottom line
is one אמה amah equals 24 equals six טפחים tefachim which is
24 אצבעות. etzbaot. Half an אמה amah is three טפחים tefachim which
is 12 אצבעות etzbaot and we said and now we have these
12 אצבעות etzbaot to divide amongst three אמה that gives us the
extra three אצבעות etzbaot and one-third. Okay, so three and a half
אצבעות etzbaot per אמה of elevation and then three and a third
אצבעות. etzbaot. שכויח. Shkoach.
That's it for today. Thank you. And what I was going to
say before, yeah, sorry, that...